dips versus bench press which is the king of upper
body exercises bodybuilding stereotypes are still
present to this day the barbell lifts are seen
as the main course they're the serious lift in
your program whereas bodyweight movements like
dips are seen as just dessert that's sprinkled
in at the end of a workout as a finisher burnout
or just for some variety there's misconceptions
about calisthenics to this day people still
believe that body weightight exercises are
inferior to barbells and dumbbells this is 2025
we understand that the body knows tension and you
can build muscle with body weightight exercise
in powerlifting dips aren't a competition lift
therefore they're seen as an accessory exercise to
build up your chest and triceps to increase your
bench beginner exercise it's not something for the
serious lifter despite the fact that the average
person can't even do 30 full range of motion
dips we're also forgetting we can add weight
to the dip for a lifetime of progressive overload
unlocking superhuman levels of strength and upper
body size the average calisnics bro looks like
he's been sculpted by a Greek god with chiseled
pecs delts and triceps using predominantly the
dip what are the pros and cons of choosing one
exercise over the other the problem with dips
is you're at the mercy of the equipment that's
available at your gym and let's be honest at most
commercial gyms the bars are either too wide or
too narrow this causes you to awkwardly flare out
if you've got this wide grip or you can barely
fit between the close setting on the dip bars
that lack of customization is a real downside
of training the dip if you can't find an option
that suits your body type you're likely to skip
the exercise and that's what most people do i'll
teach you some workarounds a bit later on being
fat makes the dip hard that's the unspoken benefit
of this exercise being leaner is challenging it's
hard to get a visible six-pack and striations
everywhere veins popping out because you have to
stick to the healthy lifestyle stay on top of your
nutrition and keep this going when you're lighter
and leaner you're going to be flying around like
a feather during dips it's this positive feedback
loop which keeps you motivated and accountable
to stick to nutrition because there's a direct
correlation with your level of body fat as well
as your dip performance the heavier you are with
excess fat the harder dips become you don't want
this extra baggage weighing you down if you're
the calisthenics enjoyer this is because it's
dead weight it's going to make it much harder
to push yourself through space let alone overcome
gravity at the same time real talk those who are
the strongest at dips have maximized their
relative strength pound-for-pound ratio by
being around 10% body fat if you're serious
about training dips you can't be going balls
deep eating junk food and excessive calories all
the time it's going to hinder your calisthenics
performance with dips you've got a greater range
of motion there's an increased stretch happening
through the anterior delts the chest as well
as the triceps which is really effective for
hypertrophy it's a closed kinetic chain exercise
you're building up your body weight strength your
stability because the hands are fixed and the
body moves the scapula is free to move around
during dips promoting healthy shoulder function
all those rotator cuff and trap muscles have to
be strong to support your main pressing muscles
in dips all that hard work is going to result in
a pair of resilient flexible and strong shoulders
when you build up that range of motion gradually
the downside of dips is it's often too challenging
for beginners to jump into straight away with
their full body weight you have to find ways to
reduce the intensity such as using an assisted dip
machine or using bands to offload body weight dips
require more shoulder mobility than the average
person has it's the hard fact it takes patient
progress over months and years for some people
to do dips with full ROM comfortably in reality
people expect to do dips on day one no problem
rushing straight into the exercise without
enough mobility is a recipe for disaster it's
not the dip's fault for causing pain and injury
it's actually our fault for not addressing our
weaknesses with scapular control flexibility
and just gradually introducing dips slowly on
the other hand when you're doing dips it's a real
skill trying to figure out where that 90° range of
motion is where your rear delt is below your elbow
takes kinesthetic awareness of where your body is
in space and a ton of practice to get consistent
when you've got one two three plates hanging
between your legs on a dip it commands respect
people look over from the other side of the gym
and they see this absolute meathead banging out
dips weight plates clanging between the thighs
intuitively people understand the dip is hard
it requires that flexibility stability and body
control which is a completely different world from
what happens during bench press unfortunately ego
lifting and the bench press have been a match made
in heaven since the first weight was hoisted many
centuries ago it's such a tempting exercise to
cheat in many ways you can just bounce the bar
off the chest you can arch the back you can lift
your bum off the bench and there's more subtle
ways of cheating where you increase the weight but
you compensate in other ways you start cutting the
range of motion or you start using a really
explosive tempo just to hoist the weight up
without any control the bench press shines because
it's an easier exercise to master for beginners by
comparison to the dip you can start with just the
bar or really light dumbbells in order to master
technique at your own pace bulking up increases
your bench almost linearly up to a certain point
you're laughing if you're packing on the kilos
because your gym lift is going to go up you've got
more cushion for the cushion improved leverages by
having that increased fat around your upper body
it actually decreases the range of motion because
you've got bigger chest shoulders and arms easier
as well the bar path distance that the barbell has
to travel is shorter because you've got a thicker
torso the lift actually becomes mechanically
easier i remember opting for the bench press
instead of doing dips when I bulked last year for
me the bench press was an enabling exercise for my
complacency it gave me this cognitive dissonance
the delusion of benching heavier because of the
surplus was actually masking my subconscious which
was saying "Hey mate your rig is getting a little
bit sloppy maybe hold off on those cheat meals
the exercise doesn't make the man dips aren't
going to make you shredded bench press won't
make you bulky there's just a price to where
your strengths lie given that benches barbells and
dumbbells are accessible in every single good gym
it's no surprise that the bench press is a popular
lift generally there's less shoulder stress when
you're doing a bench press by comparison to a
weight to dip because the shoulder flexibility
demands are less during a bench press allowing
you to hit your upper body muscles without drama
unsurprisingly the bench press has poor transfer
to calisthenics exercises don't expect to unlock
the PLCH or handstand push-up just because you can
bench two plates or more this is because with the
bench press not only are you lifting free weights
but you've got the external stability of the bench
keeping your shoulders in place it's really
tempting to run someone else's race you look
at how much they're lifting and you try and force
things you try and force progress sooner than it
actually is you got to focus on yourself despite
the temptation of the bench press being such a
comparative lift the advantage of bench press
is you've got relatability everyone asks "Hey
bro how much can you bench?" And if you say "Mate
I'm doing two plates as a warm-up three plates as
a PR." The person's mind is going to be blown no
one ever asks "Hey man how much do you dip?" And
if you say "I can do 60 kilos for a set of five."
The person will say "Is that good?" In terms of
muscle activation how does the dip compared to
the bench press for hitting the chest with the
bench press you're overloading horizontal pressing
which is going to target the entirety of your pecs
then you can also do an incline bench press to
bias the upper fibers of the chest the dip is
a vertical press and based on the body position
it's going to emphasize more of the lower pecs
as well as the sternal fibers of the chest we
just have to look at the torso angle in dips
we're leaning forwards and this puts us in more
of a horizontal pressing position this posture is
pretty comparable to that of a decline bench press
and the activation of what it does to the pecs is
very similar next up we have the arm path during
a dip you're getting tons of shoulder extension
your arms are going way back behind the torso
this is going to create a huge stretch through
the chest particularly the sternal fibers of
the pecs if you want a well-rounded physique
it's best to do both because you're training your
muscles at a variety of angles for well-developed
pecs i've got a hybrid training system that's
going to take out all the guesswork so you can
get big with weights and strong at calisthenics
becoming a well-rounded beast that's muscular
and capable here's why you should do both the dip
and the bench press in your workouts variety is
such an underrated workout principle if I had
to do only the bench press or only the dip for
the rest of my life I'd get burnt out bored and
I'd probably stop working out where's the fun in
just doing the exact same thing over and over for
the rest of your life don't limit yourself most of
you watching want to become a well-rounded beast
someone that's capable of lifting heavy weights
someone who looks like they actually lift with
muscle mass and able to move your body freely
through space with that superhuman strength unless
your goal is competing in one rep max strength say
a powerlifter doing the bench press or a street
lifter doing the weighted dip then it makes more
sense to have a balanced approach to your training
by doing both compound exercises another reason
for combining both is injury prevention as well
as movement diversity the body can handle a lot
just not a lot of the same thing over and over
when you're prioritizing just one movement with
too much frequency intensity and volume without
a break it's inherently riskier because you're
stressing your joints and tendons in a very
specific and repetitive way if it's not matched
with enough recovery it's a recipe for injury
risk in the past when all I did was dip because
I wanted to specialize in this exercise I ran into
overuse injuries in my pecs biceps as well as my
shoulders because that's all that I was doing it's
no surprise since making my program more diverse
by including multiple presses like the bench
press the dip and rotating exercises my joints
and tendons and my body at large is feeling much
healthier the truth is progress eventually stalls
no matter how perfect your program so an effective
strategy for the goal of hypertrophy is doing both
dips and bench press but swapping which comes
first in your workout week for example on day
one you start with bench press and then finish
with the dip on day two you begin with the dip
and you finish with your bench press this avoids
accommodation which is your body getting used to
doing the same thing over and over it provides
you with a novel stimulus to challenge yourself
to improve and by swapping that main lift and
accessory you're challenging yourself in a
different way in each workout here's the best
variations of the bench press and the dip to
build muscle get stronger and train painfree the
barbell bench press or the parallel bar dip these
are the first variations which come to mind when
you think of the exercise don't get me wrong these
are great ways to train if they feel okay but if
either exercise is giving you grief you don't have
to suffer in silence or give up on these classic
lifts completely this is where exercise variation
comes in please please experiment with different
types of equipment to get the benefits without
the pain dumbbells are a great choice for benching
and they might just feel better on your joints and
tendons dumbbells offer greater range of motion
because you can stretch well below chest height
by comparison to your standard barbell bench
they also demand more stability than barbells
which can make your rotator cuff more robust at
the shoulder making you more bulletproof you're
benefiting from a unilateral focused press where
you're getting an equal stimulus on both left and
right sides without your arm dominance taking
over like it would on a barbell bench switching
to calisthenics rings are the perfect substitute
if you're sick and tired of using bad parallel bar
equipment at the gym this is the calisthenics
equivalent of using dumbbells the freedom of
movement feels incredible when you're doing your
dips on this equipment many people swear by the
rings for finally making it possible to train
their dips painfree unlike which happens on the
parallel bars in some cases with ring dips you're
going to develop a pair of flexible strong robust
shoulders and of course watermelon pecs if your
mind isn't blown from all that information it's
safe to say that both exercises are valuable
for building upper body strength and muscle
size you're going to be missing out on gains if
you're not bench pressing and doing dips the sum
is greater than the parts just doing bench press
has limitations only doing dips is going to leave
you with weak links combining both is where
the magic happens bam that is the next video
I would like you to watch on the Fitness FAQ's
YouTube channel to continue learning and leveling